Guide to the Abraham & Straus collection ARC.223
Brooklyn Historical Society
Abraham & Straus collection
1886-1995
Brooklyn Historical Society
Abraham & Straus
Wechsler & Abraham
ARC.223
0.25 Linear Feet in one manuscript box and one oversize folder.
1 Gigabytes in fifteen files.
Various materials relating to Abraham & Straus, a major department store founded in Brooklyn by Abraham Abraham and Joseph Wechsler in 1865. The store became part of Macy's department stores in 1995.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction. Please consult library staff for access to digitized recordings.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Accessions 1977.242 and V1990.009 were the gifts of Juli Daves and Harriet Stryker-Rodda, 1965. Accession 1986.037 was purchased from Xerxes Fine and Rare Books and Documents, 1986. Accession 2009.013 was the gift of Armida Giglio, 2009. Digitized recordings of the Walter Rothschild Sr. 40th anniversary celebration dinner were the gift of Michael J. Lisicky, with the support of Walter (Trip) Rotschild III, 2017.
Existence and Location of Copies
Item-level description and digital versions of two images from the collection are available for searching via the image database in the library under the object ID prefixes V1990.1 and V1997.87.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 5 series by type. Within each series, the arrangement is roughly chronological.
Historical Note
Abraham & Straus was a major department store founded in Brooklyn by Abraham Abraham and Joseph Wechsler in 1865. Originally called Wechsler & Abraham and located at 285 Fulton Street, the store was so successful that it moved to a new and larger location at the corner of Fulton and Hoyt Streets in 1885. The name of the store changed to Abraham & Straus in 1893 when the Straus family, partners of Macy's department stores, bought out Wechsler's interest in the store. By 1965, Abraham & Straus had become the third largest department store in the United States, with several branches in and surrounding the New York City area in addition to its flagship location at Fulton and Hoyt Streets. The store became part of Macy's department stores in 1995. Until 2024, the original Abraham & Straus location on Fulton and Hoyt Streets continued to operate under the Macy's name.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Brooklyn Historical Society ephemera collection (ARC.272), Folder: Business and Businesses -- Abraham and Straus
Brooklyn ephemera collection (BCMS.0007), Folder: Stores & Shops: Abraham and Straus
Records of the Brooklyn Council for Social Planning (BCMS.0039),Series 7: Related non-government agencies, Subseries 7.5: Other related agencies, Folder: Abraham and Straus [A&S]
Downtown Brooklyn Development Association records (1979.021), Folder: Abraham and Straus Garage
Allen J. Kone collection of Brooklyn postcards (2016.014), Section: Stores
Brooklyn and New York City business catalogs collection (1986.047)
Brooklyn Daily Eagle photographs (BCMS.0002): Various employee portraits
Scope and Contents
Series 1: Publications includes a catalog dating from 1886, when the store was known as Wechsler & Abraham; an 80th anniversary booklet from 1945; and newsletters dating from 1941-1995.
Series 2: Centennial includes correspondence between Abraham & Straus employee Juli Daves and Harriet Stryker-Rodda, Archivist at the Long Island Historical Society, regarding research for the store's centennial; a press kit with releases, including a detailed history of the business; newspaper clippings; and press photographs. The photographs depict Abraham & Straus founder Abraham Abraham; Chairman of the Board and Chief Executive Officer Sidney L. Solomon; President Walter N. Rothschild, Jr.; and the Wechsler & Abraham store at its original Fulton Street location. They have biographical and historical information attached to their versos.
Series 3: Ephemera and images includes a metal tag, color postcard, various printed ephemera and a color 4x6 photograph of the store's facade from 1995. There is also an oversize print showing an aerial view of the flagship Abraham & Straus store at its location on Fulton and Hoyt Streets, along with other parts of Downtown Brooklyn, circa 1893.
Series 4: Armida Giglio materials consists of material collected by longtime Abraham & Straus employee Armida Giglio and given to the Brooklyn Historical Society in 2009. These materials include store directories, branded shopping bags, centennial materials, and various printed ephemera.
Finally, Series 5: Digital materials consists of digitized recordings of the Walter Rothschild Sr. 40th anniversary celebration dinner in 1953.
Business enterprises -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Catalogs; Centennial celebrations, etc.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Department stores -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Department stores -- New York (State) -- Kings County -- History; Directories; Histories; Newsletters; Photographs; Postcards; Retail trade -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Shopping centers -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Sound recordings; WAVE (format); Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Fulton Street (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Wechsler & Abraham; Abraham & Straus
- Series 1: Publications
  - Wechsler and Abraham catalogue, 1886; 1986.037 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Purchase from Xerxes Fine and Rare Books, 1986.
  - Spotlight newsletter, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Some or all issues were the gift of Armida Giglio, 2009.
  - 80th anniversary booklet, 1945
  - Specials newsletter, 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Coast to Coast newsletter (Federated Department Stores, Inc.), Spring 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series 2: Centennial, 1977.242
  - Harriet Stryker-Rodda and Juli Daves correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Press kit folder and press releases, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Press images, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes a photographic copy of a woodcut image of the original store and photographic portrait images of Abraham Abraham, Walter N. Rothschild, Jr., and Sidney L. Solomon.
  - Clippings, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series 3: Ephemera and images
  - Metal tag, circa 1940s; 2025.009 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Gift of Jane F. Levey, 2025.
  - Postcard of revolving Christmas tree, circa 1950s-60s; V1997.087 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Receipt, 1956; Warrener, Gayla (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Gift of Gayla Warrener, 2025.
    Warrener, Gayla
  - Department Managers letter, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Fulton Mall Improvement Association booklet, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Oversize flyer, Brooklyn Bridge centennial, 1983 (Box OS-35)
  - Macy's booklet, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Images, circa 1893, 1995 (Box 1, Box OS-35)
    One oversize black and white print depicting the A&S building circa 1893; one color 4x6 print of the new Macy's sign on the building, 1995.
- Series 4: Armida Giglio materials, 2009.013
  Gift of Armida Giglio, 2009.
  The donor also gifted some or all of the Spotlight newsletters in Series 1 and may have given other materials in the collection.
  - A&S directories, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Shopping bags, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Clippings and ephemera, 1965-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Includes centennial materials, 1965, and 1980s ephemera.
- Series 5: Digital materials
  - Recordings of the Walter Rothschild Sr. 40th anniversary celebration dinner, 1953 (Item digital files)